多年以来许多原始密码学构造被发现是不可靠的
Over the years many natural cryptographic
constructions were found to be insecure.
使得现代密码学成为一门严谨的科学
In response, modern cryptography was
developed as a rigorous science where
它的解释总是伴随着对安全性的证明
constructions are always accompanied by a
proof of security. The language used to
对安全性的描述是基于离散概率
在此节和下一小节中
describe security relies on discreet
probability. In this segment and the next,
我将简要的回顾一下离散概率
我提到的这篇维基教科书里的文章
I'll give a brief overview of discreet
probability, and I point to this Wiki
有很长的一段介绍
离散概率总是
books article over here for a longer
introduction. Discrete probability is
用全集定义，我将其用U来表示
并且设它为一个有穷集合
always defined over a universe which I'll
denote by u and this universe in our case
事实上，我们的整体很常见的可能就是
is always going to be a finite set. In
fact very commonly our universe is going
所有n位字符串的集合
这里用01的N次集合来表示
to be simply the set of all n bit strings
which here is denoted by zero one to the
比如0、1集合的平方是两位字符串
n. So for example the set zero one squared
is the set of all two bit strings which
00，01，10，11的集合
happens to be the string zero, zero, zero
one, One, zero, and one, one. So there are
所以这个集合里有4个元素
一般来说，0、1的N次集合
four elements in this set, and more
generally in the set zero one to the N,
有2^n个元素
此集合U的概率分布
there are two to the N elements. Now a
probability distribution over this
可以仅用函数P来表示
universe U is simply a function which I'll
denote by P, and this function, what it
该函数为全局中的每一个元素赋一个0到1之间的值
does, is it assigns to every element in
the universe a number between zero and
这个值就叫做此集合特定元素的权重或概率
one. And this number is what I'll call the
weight or the probability of that
现在对函数P只有一个必要条件
particular element in the universe. Now
there's only one requirement on this
就是所有权重之和为1
function P, and that is that the sum of
all the weights, sum up to one. That is,
也就是说，如果我把此集合内每个元素X的概率相加
if I sum the probability of all elements X
in the universe, what I end up with is the
最终会得到1。让我们看一个非常简单的例子
全体二位字符串
number one. So let's look at a very simple
example looking back to our 2-bit
00，01,10,11
你可以考虑如下概率分布
universe. So 00，01, ,10 and 11 And you
can consider the following probability
例如，P(00)=1/2
distribution Which, for example, assigns
to the element 00, the probability one
P(01)=1/8
half. The elements 01, we assign the
probability 1/8th, to ten we assign the
P(10)=1/4
P(11)=1/8
probability one quarter and to eleven we
assign the probability 1/8th. Okay we can
可以看到如果把这些数字的和加起来那么结果为一
see that if we sum up these numbers in
fact we get one which means that this
也就是概率P符合概率分布条件
probability P is in fact the probability
distribution. Now what these number mean
现在这些数字的意思是，如果我从这个概率分布中取样
is that if I sample from this probability
distribution I'll get the string 00 with
那么我得到字符串00的概率是1/2
01的概率是1/8,并以此类推
probability one half I'll get the string
01 with probability 1/8th and so on and so
所以现在我们理解了概率分布的含义
forth. So now that we understand what a
probability distribution is, let's look at
就让我们来看一下两个概率分布的经典例子
two classic examples of probability
distributions. The first one is what's
第一个是均匀分布
called the uniform distribution. The
uniform distribution assigns to every
均匀分布为集合中的每一个元素分配完全一样的权重
element in the universe, exactly the same
weight. I'm gonna use U between two bars
记|U|为总体U的大小
即总体的元素个数
to denote the size of the universe U. That
is the number of elements in the universe,
既然我们希望权重的总和为一
且每个元素的权重相同
and since we want the sum of all the
weights to sum out to one, and we want all
这意味着总体中的每个元素X
these weights to be equal, what this means
is that for every element X in the
我们为之赋以1/U的概率
如果我们再详细地看一下例子
universe, we assign a probability of one
over U. So in particular if we look at our
均匀分布和两位字符串的集合
example, the uniform distribution and the
set of two bits strings, would
我们将会简单地给每一个字符分配1/4的权重
simply assign one-quarter the weight,
one-quarter to each one of these strings
显然所有权重的和加起来为1
And clearly that, the sum of all the
weights sums up to one. Well again, what
再者说，这意味着如果我从这个分布中随机取样
this means is that if I sample at random
from this distribution, I'll get a uniform
我将会得到所有两位字符串的均匀样本
因此所有这些4位（2位）字符串在此概率分布中
sample across all our 2-bit strings So all
of these 4-bit strings are equally likely
被取样的概率相等
另外一个非常常见的分布是
to be sampled by this distribution.
Another distribution that's very common is
点分布
点分布的主要做法是
what's called a point distribution at the
point X0 And what this point distribution
将所有的权重分配到一个点X0上
does is basically it puts all the weight
on a single point, namely X0. So here we
我们将所有权重都赋给X0，自然在此总体中
assign to the point X0 all the weight, one
And then to all other points in the
我们将其他点的权重赋0
另外我想解释一下
universe, we assign the weight zero And by
the way, I want to point out that this,
这个倒着的A表示任意，所以这一切说明了，
inverted, A here should be read as, for
all. So all this says is, that for all X
所有不为X0的X的概率为0
that are not equal to X zero, the
probability of that X is zero. So again
再一次回到我们的例子，比如点分布中
going back to our example a point
distribution for example, that would put
将概率全部只分给字符串1-0
即P(10)=1
all its mass on the string 1-0, would
assign probability one to the string 1-0
而其他的字符串概率均为0
所以如果我从这个分布中取样
and zero to all other strings. So now if I
sample from this distribution pretty much
我将总保证能得到字符串10
而不会得到其它的字符串
I'm always guaranteed to always sample the
string 1-0 and never sample any of the
现在我们知道分配是什么了
other strings. So now we know what a
distribution is, and I just want to make
我还想再说最后一点
可以这样做的原因是因为总体U为有限集
one last point, and that is that because
this universe U is always gonna be a
所以我们可以写出U中每一个元素分配到的权重
finite set up for us, we can actually
write down the weights that the
并且可以用一个向量表示整个分布
distribution assigns to every element in
U, and represent the entire distribution
比如说，如果你观察所有的3位字符串
as a vector. So, here for example, if you
look at the universe of an all 3-bit
我们可以逐个写下
strings, we can literally write down the
ways that the distribution assigns to the
P(000)、P(001)等等
string 000, then the way that distribution
assigns to the string 001 And so on, and
我们可以把这些概率写成向量形式
so forth. And you can see that we can write
this as a vector, in this case it will be
这样的向量是8维的三位字符串有8个
a vector of dimension eight, there will
be, there are eight strings of 3-bits as a
基本上整个分布用这8个实数的向量表示
result basically the entire distribution
is captured by this vector of eight real
实数的范围都是0到1。下一步我要做的是
numbers, in the range of all zero to one.
The next thing I wanna do is define the
定义事件的概念。考虑我们整体的子集A
concept of an event. So consider a subset
A of our universe And I, I'll define the
定义子集A的概率为A集合中所有元素的权重
probability of the subsets to be simply
the sum of the weights of all the elements
换句话说，我将把A中X的概率求和
in the set A. In other words, I'm summing
over all X and A, the weights of these
因为整体的权重和应为1
elements X in the set A, Now because the
sum over the entire universe of all
这意味着如果求和
weights needs to be one. This means that
if we sum, well if you look at the
整体的概率应为1
probability of the entire universe,
basically we get one. And if we look at
如果我们观察整体的一个子集的概率，我们会得到一个介于0和1之间的数
the probability of a subset of the
universe, we're gonna get some number in
我们说集合A的概率是一个介于0和1之间的和
the interval zero to one And we say that
the probability of this set A, is the sum
那么整体的子集A就叫做一个事件
which is a number between zero and one.
And I'll tell you that a subset A of the
集合A的概率就叫做这一事件的的概率
universe is called an event. And the
probability of the set A is called the
让我们看一个简单的例子，假定我们
probability of that event. So let's look
at a simple example. So suppose we look at
有集合U，它包含所有8位字符串，好吧？
the universe u, which consists of all
8-bit strings, right? So the size of this
所以集合的大小是256，因为它有256个8位字符串，我们本质上
universe u is 256 because there are 256
8-bit strings. Essentially we're looking
是在看所有可能的256个字节值，现在我们定义以下事件
at all byte values, all 256 possible byte
values. Now let's define the following
基本上事件将包含整体中所有的8个字节
event. Basically the event is gonna
contain all bytes so all 8-bit strings
比如低两位为11的字符串
in the universe such that the two
least significant bits of the byte happens
比如01011010，它是整体的一个元素
to be eleven So for example, if we look at
01011010 that's an element in the universe
但它不在集合A中，如果我们把这个0改为1
that's not in the set A, but if we choose
a zero to a one. Then that's an element of
它就是集合A中的元素，现在我们来看看全局U上的均匀分布
the universe which gives in our set A. And
now let's look at the uniform distribution
现在我问你事件A的概率是多少？
over the universe U and let me ask you
what is the probability of the, of the
当我们随机选择一个字节
event A? So what is the probability that
when we choose a random byte, the two
字节最后两位正好是11的概率是多少
least significant bits of that byte
happens to be one, one? Well the answer is
结果是1/4，而且并不难找到一个能说服你自己的正确解释
one-fourth, and the reason that's true is
because it's not too difficult to convince
256个字符串中，有64个这样的字节
yourself that of the 256 eight bit
strings, exactly 64 of them, one quarter
也就是1/4的字符串以11结尾
考虑到均匀分布
of them, end in one, one. And the
probability of each string is, we're
每个字符串的概率是1/|U|
looking at the uniform distribution or
probability of each string is exactly one
即1/256
over the size of the universe, mainly one
over 256. And the product of these, you
64个元素每个权重1/256，一共是1/4
know, 64 elements, each one has weight one
over 256 is exactly one-fourth, which is
这就是事件A的概率，事件概率有一个简单的范围
the probability of the event A that we're
looking at. So a very simple bound on the
叫做并集上界
假设我们有两个事件A1和A2
probability of events is called the union
bound. So imagine we have two events a1
它们都是全集U的子集，我们想知道
and a2. So these are both subsets of some
universe U Snd we wanna know what is the
事件A1发生或者事件A2发生的概率，即P(A1∪A2)
probability that either A1 occurs, or A2
occurs In other words, what is the
符号∪表示两个集合的并集
probability of the union of these two
events? This little U here denotes the
并集上界指出了
union of the two sets. So the union bound
tells us that the probability that either
P(A1∪A2)≤P(A1)+P(A2)
A1 occurs or A2 occurs is basically less
than the sum of the two probabilities. And
这是显而易见的，在这幅图中
that's actually quite easy to see. So
simply look at this picture here, you can
观察这两个概率的和
see that when we look at, at the sum of
the two probabilities, we're basically
它们分别是A1中元素概率的和和A2中元素的和
summing the probability of all the
elements in A1, all the elements in A2 And
你会意识到我们好像把两个集合重叠部分的元素加了两次
you realized, we kind of double-summed
these elements in the intersection. They
使得在右边求和时算了两次
get summed twice here on the right hand
side And as a result, the sum of the two
结果使得这两个概率的和大于等于P(A1∪A2)
probabilities is going to be larger or
larger than or equal to, the actual
这就是经典的并集上界定义
probability of the union of A1 and A2. So
that's the classic union bound And in fact
如果两个事件不相交，换句话说它们的交集为空
I'll tell you that if the two events are
disjoint, in other words they're
那么这个式子就变成
intersection is empty, in that case if we
look at the sum, at the probability that
P(A1∪A2)=P(A1)+P(A2)
either A-1 or A02 happens, that's exactly
equal to the sum of the two probabilities.
怎么样？我们将在整门课使用这些结论
Okay? So we'll use these facts here and
there throughout the course. So just to be
让我们理清一下，这个不等关系一直存在
除非两个事件不相交，
clear, the inequality holds always But
when the two events are disjoint, then in
那时候取等号。让我们看一个简单的例子
fact we get an equality over here. So
let's look at a simple example. Suppose
事件A1是所有以11结尾的n位字符串的集合
our, event A1 is the set of all n-bit
stings that happen to end in 1-1 And
假设A2是所有以11开头的n位字符串
suppose A2 is the set of all n-bit strings
that happen to begin with 1-1. Okay, so N
n设定为H或某个大数，问事件A1或事件A2发生的概率是多少？
thinks of it as H or some large number and
I'm asking that what is the probability
换句话说，如果在全体U中均匀取样
that either a one happens or a two
happens, In other words if I sample
最后2位为11
uniformly from the universe U, what is the
probability that either the least
或者最前2位是11的概率是多少？
significant bits are one, one or the most
significant digits are one, one. Well as
我们说这个概率记为P(A1∪A2)
we said that's basically the probability
of the union of A1 and A2. We know that
其中每一个事件的概率由前可知为1/4
the probability of each one of these
events is one-quarter by what we just did
因此根据并集上限
previous slide And therefore by the union
bound the probability of the
“或”的概率为P(A1)+P(A2)
‘or’. Is, you know, a quarter of
the probability of A1, plus the
即1/4+1/4,我们这就证明了
probability of A2, which is a quarter plus
a quarter. And we just proved that the
最前2位是11的概率或者最后两位是11的概率
probability of seeing 1-1 in the most
significant bit, or 1-1 least significant
比1/2小，这是一个简单的例子
bit, is less than one-half. So that's a
simple example of how we might go about
说明了我们如何用并集上界来界定两个事件中一个事件发生的概率
using the Union Bound to bound the
probability that one of two events might
下一个我们需要定义的概念是随机变量
happen. The next concept we need to
define, is what's called a random
随机变量是比较直观的对象
variable. Now, random variables are fairly
intuitive objects. But unfortunately the
但令人遗憾的是随机变量的正式定义不好理解
formal definition of a random variable can
be a little confusing. So what I'll do
所以我将要做的是，给出一个例子，并希望它足够直观
is, I'll give an example, and hopefully
that will be clear enough. So formally, a
形式上定义随机变量为X，它是从全体到某个集合V的函数
random variable denoted say, by X. Is a
function, from the universe into some set
集合V就是随机变量取值的地方
V And we say that this set V is where the
random variable takes its values. So let's
让我们看一个具体的例子。假设我们有一个随机变量X
look at a particular example. So suppose
we have a random variable x And this
这个随机变量映射到集合01中
random variable maps into the set 01. So
the values of this random variable are
所以这个随机变量的值为0或1，也就是基础的1位。
going to be either zero or one. So, one
bit, basically. Now, this random variable
现在，这个随机变量映射我们的全体，也就是所有2位二元字符串的定义域[0,1]^n
maps our universe, which is the center of
all n bit binary strings, 01 to the n
它是怎么做的？从全体中给出一个具体样本
And how does it do it? Well, given a
particular sample in the universe, a
n位字符串y。随机变量将会输出
particular n-bit string y. What the
random variable will do is simply output
y的最后一位。这就是整个随机变量
the least significant bit of y And that's
it. That's the whole random variable. So,
现在我要问，假设有一在集合[0,1]^n上的随机分布
now let me ask you. Suppose we look at a
uniform distribution on the set zero one
问这个随机变量输出0的概率是多少？
to the n. Let me ask you what is the
probability that this random variable
输出1的概率是多少？
output zero and what is the probability
that a random variable outputs one? Well
你可以看到答案分别是1/2,1/2.让我们来推导下为什么会这样
you can see that the answers are half and
half. Well let's just reason  through
这张图展示了全体的情况
why that's the case. So here we have a
picture showing the universe and the
和可能的输出空间。所以变量可能的输出是0或1
possible output space. And so in this case
the variable can output a zero or a one.
变量输出0在哪？当总体中的样本最低位为0时
When there is a variable output zero,
there is a variable output zero when the
当变量输出0时
sample in the universe happens to be, to
have its least inefficient bit
变量为1时总体中的样本
be set to zero. In variable one, output
one When the sample in the universe
最低有效位为1。如果随机均匀选择字符串
happens to have its least significant bit
set to one. Well, if choose strings
那么我们选到以0结尾的字符串的概率为1/2
uniformly at random, the probability that
we choose a string that has its least
随机变量结果为0的概率也为1/2
significant bits set to zero is exactly
one half Which the random variable output
同样的如果我们随机选取一个n位字符串
zero with a probability of exactly
one-half. Similarly, if we choose a random
最后一位为1的概率也是1/2
n-bit string, the probability that the
least significant bit is equal to one is
我们说随机变量结果为1的概率也是1/2
also one-half. And so we say that the
random variable output's one, also with
现在，在更一般的情况如果我们有一个随机变量
exactly probability of one-half. Now,
more generally, if we have a random
在一个确定集合V中取值，这个随机变量实际上可以推出
variable taking values in a certain set v,
then this random variable actually induces
集合V的分布。这里我们以符号形式
a distribution on this set v. And here, I
just wrote a, kind of a, in symbols, what
表示这个分布的意义。不过这其实是很好解释的
this distribution means But it's actually
very easy to explain. Essentially, what it
本质上它表示这个变量结果为V。因为我们在全体中随机选取元素
says is that the variable outputs v
Basically, with the same probability that
所以概率是相等，然后我们应用函数X
if we sample a random element in the
universe, and, and then we apply the
问输出为v的可能性是多少？
function x. We ask, how likely is it that
the output is actually equal to v? So formally
形式上说P(X=v)为我们在总体中随机取出一个元素
we say that the probability that X outputs
V, is the same as the probability of the
在函数X的作用下
event That when we sample a random element
in the universe, we fall into the pre
结果落在v的原象中的概率。如果这样不清楚，也不要紧
image of V under the function X And again,
if this wasn't clear, it's not that
你需要知道的是，随机变量在特定的集合V中取值
important. All you need to know is that a
random variable takes values in a
而且可以推导出集合V的概率分布
particular set V, and in, induces a
distribution on that set V. Now there's a
有一个特别重要的随机变量叫均匀随机变量
particularly important random variable
called a uniform random variable. And it's
它基本上是如你期望的那样进行定义。那么我们说U是某有限集
basically defined as you would expect. So
let's say that U is some finite
比如所有N位二元字符串
set For example the set of all N bit
binary strings, and we're gonna denote a
我们用R表示随机变量，从集合U均匀地取样
random variable R that's basically
sample's uniformly from the set U by this
用这个有点搞笑的箭头加上R表示，
little funny arrow with a little R on top
of it. In this, again the notes that the
讲义上的随机变量R是集合U上的均匀随机变量
random variable R is literally a uniform
random variable sampled over the set U. So
用符号表示为所有a∈ U
in symbols what's this means is that for
all elements A in the universe, the
P(r=a)=1/|U|，如果你坚持使用
probability that R is equal to A is simply
R one over U. And if you want to stick to
均匀随机变量的正式定义，这个也不那么重要
the formal definition of a, of a uniform
variable, it's not actually that important
但我想说从形式上均匀随机变量是恒等式
But I would just say that formally the
uniform random variable is an identity
也就是说 对所有x∈ U  R(x)=X ，只是为了确保这足够清楚
function namely R(x)is equal to
X for all X in the universe So just to see
我要问你们一个简单的问题。假设
that this is clear, let me ask you a
simple puzzle. Suppose we have a uniform
我们有一个2位字符串的均匀随机变量全体，即集合为01, 10, 00, 11
random variable over 2-bit strings, so
over the set, 01, ten, one and now, let's
定义一个新的随机变量x，表示将R的第1位和第2位相加
define a new random variable X to basicall
y sum the first and second bits of R. That
即X=r1+r2，R的第1位和第2位相加
is, X simply is the sum of R1 and R2, the
first and second bits of R, treating those
把这2位当做整数，例如R=00，那么X=0+0=0
bits as integers. So, for example, if, r
happens to be 00, then x will be 0+0,
所以我要问，P(x=2)是多少？
which is zero. So let me ask you, what is
the probability that x is = to two? So
不难看出答案是1/4,因为
it's not difficult to see that the answer
is exactly, one-fourth because, basically
x=2的情况只有R=11
the only way that x is equal to two is if
r happens to be 1,1 but the probability
但是R=11的概率只有1/4,因为R是在所有2位字符串中均匀分布的
that r is equal to 1,1 is basically
one-fourth because r is uniform over the
最后一个我想在这一节定义的概念是
set of all two bit strings. The last
concept I want to define in this segment
随机算法，我相信你们都熟悉确定性算法
is what's called a randomized algorithm.
So I'm sure you're all familiar with
这些算法对特定的输入数据
deterministic algorithms. These are
algorithms that basically take a
总是产生相同的输出，记为Y
particular, input data, as input, and they
always produce the same output, say Y. So
如果我们将算法在同样输入下运行一百遍，我们总会得到同样的输出
if we run the algorithm a hundred times on
the same input, we'll always get the same
所以可以把确定算法看做一个函数
output. So you can think of a
deterministic algorithm as a function that
给出一个确定输入数据M，总会准确地产生同样的输出A(m)
given a particular input data, M, will
always produce exactly the same output, A
随机算法有点不同，在随机算法中
of M. A randomized algorithm is a little
different, in that, as before, it takes
依旧将取数据M作为输入，不过还有一个隐形参数R
the input data M as input, but it also
has an implicit argument called R, where
R在每次运行算法的时候都会重新取样，特别的
this R is sampled anew every time the
algorithm is run. And in particular this R
R是在所有N位字符串中均匀随机取样的
is sampled uniformly at random from the
set of all N-bit strings, for some
N任意指定，现在的情况是每次我们在输入M下运行算法
arbitrary N. Now what happens is every
time we run the algorithm on a particular
都会得到一个不同的输出，因为每次的R都不一样
input M we're gonna get a different output
because a different R is generated every
所以我们第一次运行算法会得到一个输出
time. So the first time we run the
algorithm we get one output. The second
第二次运行算法产生一个新R，我们又会得到一个不同的输出
time we run the algorithm a new R is
generated and we get a different output.
第三次运行算法又会产生一个新R，我们又会得到另一个不同的输出
The third time we run the algorithm a new
R is generated and we get a third output
以此类推。所以想成随机算法其实就是定义一个随机变量
and so on. So really the way to think
about a randomized algorithm is it's
对吧？给出一个特定输入信息M
actually defining a random variable.
Right? So given a particular input
它就定义了一个随机变量
message, M, it's defining a random
variable which is, defining a distribution
也就是定义了一个此算法的所有可能输出集合的分布概率，在给定输入M的情况下
over the set of a [laugh] possible outputs
of this algorithm, given the input, M. So
所以要记住的事情是每次运行随机算法，它的输出都会变化
the thing to remember is that the output
of a randomized algorithm changes every
事实上，算法本身定义了一个分布和所有可能输出的集合
time you run it And in fact, the algorithm
defines a distribution and the set of all
让我们看一个特定的例子，假设我们有一个随机算法
possible outputs. So let's look at a
particular example. So suppose we have a
以M为输入，当然也有隐性输入
randomized algorithm that takes as input a
message M And of course it also takes an
也就是这个字符串，用来使过程随机化
implicate input which is this random
string that is used to randomize its
现在这个算法要做的是以这个随机字符串为输入
operation. So now what the algorithm will
do is simply will encrypt the message M
加密信息M。所以这基本上定义了一个随机变量
using the random string as input. So this
basically defines a random variable. This
此随机变量取值于信息M的加密结果
random variable takes values that are
encryptions of the message M And really
这个随机变量其实是定义在均匀密匙下
what this random, random variable is it's
a distribution over the set of all
信息M全部可能的加密结果上的概率分布。所以重点要记住的是
possible encryptions of the message M
under a uniform key. So the main point to
就算每次运行随机算法的时候
remember is that even though the inputs to
a randomized algorithm might always be the
输入可能总是相同的，你也将会得到一个不同的输出
same every time you run the randomized
algorithm you're gonna get a different
好了，这一节就结束了，我们将在下一节
output. Okay So, that concludes this
segment, and we'll see a bit more discrete
讨论更多关于离散概率的内容
probability in the next segment.